Guide to the Long Island Early Manuscripts Collection 1974.003
Brooklyn Historical Society
Long Island Early Manuscripts collection
1659-1861
Center for Brooklyn History
Higbie, Hamilton A.
Wilder, Frank
Townsend, Arthur O.
Seward, William
Benson, Robert
Clinton, George, 1739-1812
Child, Isaac
1974.003
0.30 Linear Feet in one half manuscript box and two folders in an oversize box (OS-38).
The collection contains correspondence, land deeds, wills, and legal and official documents, mainly related to 18th century Long Island. Includes materials related to enslaved people and Native Americans.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Immediate source of acquisition unknown. Formally accessioned in 1974.
Arrangement
Materials have been grouped by subject.
Biographical / Historical
This collection was likely assembled by BHS staff from multiple donations at an unknown date.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, legal and official documents, land deeds, wills, and two accounts of dreams or visions, one apocalyptic and the other martial and religious. The majority of the collection relates to late 17th through early 19th century Long Island, but a few documents concern Massachusetts during the same period. It contains documents relating to slavery (an enslaved person is included in the property bequeathed in a will and there is a bill of sale for a young enslaved Black woman) and Native Americans (multiple land deeds) and includes items of interest bearing on early LI families: Conkling of Easthampton, Hendrickson of South Hempstead, Udall of Islip, Willets of Islip, and Whitman of Huntington. Significant subjects include: Abraham Lincoln, George Clinton, and Wyandanch.
Wills |z New York (State); Deeds; Military commissions; Correspondence; Enslaved people -- bills of sale; Land titles; Higbie, Hamilton A.; Wilder, Frank; Townsend, Arthur O.; Whiting, Samuel; Hendrickson, John; Peltrow, Elias; L'Hommedieu, Samuel; Conkling family; Strong, Selah; Nicoll, William; Smith, Richard; Nicolls, Matthias; Townsend, Thomas; Griffing, Robert; Youngs, Benjamin; Udall family; Whitman family; Willets family; Elwell, Jonathan, Jr; Nesmith, Thomas; Nesmith, James; L'Hommedieu, Ezra; Floyd, William; Lubbertse, Frederick; Wyandanch, Sachem, circa 1620-1659
- Petition for the construction of a Turnpike, circa 1800 (Box A0100, Folder 1)
- Appointment of Samuel Whiting as U.S. Consul, signed by Abraham Lincoln, 1861 (Box A0100, Folder 2)
- Conkling Family wills and deeds of sale, 1721-1770 (Box A0100, Folder 3)
- Will of John Hendrickson, 1792 (Box A0100, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous Long Island Land Records, 1665-1683 (Box A0100, Folder 5)
- Long Island Military Commissions, 1761-1772 (Box A0100, Folder 6)
- Long Island Military List of Officers, circa 1780 (Box A0100, Folder 7)
- Southold, Long Island, Land Conveyance, 1719 (Box A0100, Folder 8)
- Uddall Family bills, correspondence, land conveyance, and legal documents, 1809-1857 (Box A0100, Folder 9)
- Quaker Record, Westbury, Long Island, 1754 (Box A0100, Folder 10)
- Willets Family land conveyance and affidavits, 1792-1817 (Box A0100, Folder 11)
- Whitman Family land conveyance, will, and financial accounts, 1704-1791 (Box A0100, Folder 12)
- Massachusetts Miscellaneous Land Deeds and Legal Document, 1727-1805 (Box A0100, Folder 13)
- Land Conveyances, Wills, Dreams, and Correspondence, 1671-1800 (Box A0100, Folder 14)
- Queens County, NY, bill of sale, marriage license, and power of attorney, 1758-1777 (Box A0100, Folder 15)
- Part of a letter from William Seward, pasted on board (Box OS-38, Folder 2)
- Extract of a letter by William Seward describing the policy of the United States government, 1861 (Box OS-38, Folder 6)